Register of the Alexander H. Van Keuren, 1899-1962
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexander H. Van Keuren,
1899-1962
74011
Van Keuren, Alexander H., 1881-1966.
8 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 8 envelopes 5.05 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, notes, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia, relating to the Naval Research Laboratory, Anacostia Station, Washington, D.C., and to the London Naval Conference and the Geneva Disarmament Conference
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States. Naval Research Laboratory (Washington, D.C.); United States. Navy--Officers.; Conference for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments (1932-1934: Geneva); London Naval Conference (1930); Disarmament.; Navies.; Peace.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Armed Forces.
Biographical Note
1881, March 9 Born, Howell, Michigan
1903 Graduated from the Naval Academy
1908 Master of Science, Massachusetts Institute of Technology
1912-1916 Served at the Mare Island Navy Yard and Superintending Constructor for Submarines at the Union Iron Works in San Francisco
1916-1920 Served in the Design Division of the Bureau of Construction and Repair, Department of the Navy
1927 Secretary, Naval War College
1930 Technical advisor, London Naval Conference
1932 Technical advisor, General Disarmament Conference, Geneva
1936 Assisted in exploratory tests on fireproof construction of ships
1936-1937 Superintending Constructor for the Navy at the New York Shipbuilding Corporation
1937-1939 Industrial manager, Navy Yard, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
1939-1940 Chief, Bureau of Construction and Repair, Department of the Navy
1940-1942 Assistant Chief, Bureau of Ships
1942 Chief, Bureau of Ships Coordinator of Shipbuilding for the Naval Establishment
1942 Received Legion of Merit Award
1942-1944 Director, Naval Research Laboratory, Anacostia Station
1946 Retired
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1899-1962. (1-3.)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- NAVAL RESEARCH LABORATORY, ANACOSTIA STATION (Washington, D.C.), OFFICE FILE, 1942-1944. (3-4.)
  Correspondence and memoranda, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- NAVY DEPARTMENT ORDERS AND MEMORANDA, 1909-1945 (4.)
- SUBJECT FILE, ca. 1900-1960 (5-7.)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, lists, notes, printed matter, etc., arranged alphabetically by subject
- MISCELLANY, ca. 1900-1960. (7-8.)
  Clippings, notes, printed matter, memorabilia, and oversize items
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1899-1962
  - Abbott, John S., 1952, 1957-1958 (Box 1.)
  - Ancrum, W., 1948, 1953, 1956, 1958
  - Anderson, W. S., 1949-1950, 1952-1953, 1955, 1958, 1964
  - Barber, Margaret, 1958
  - Battles, D. R., 1904
  - Belknap, Charles, 1949
  - Brockett, W. A., 1966
  - Burrows, J. C., 1904
  - Cleary, J. F., 1951-1954, 1956-1958, 1960-1961
  - Cooke, Henry D., 1946-1947, 1951-1952, 1955, 1957-1958
  - Court, A. B., 1925-1926
  - Davis, Milton, 1949, 1954
  - Department of the Navy
    - Bureau of Construction and Repair, 1926-1927
    - Bureau of Navigation, 1930, 1932
    - Bureau of Supplies and Accounts, 1952
    - Naval History Division
    - Office of the Chief of Naval Operations
  - Fisher, C. W., 1925-1926
  - Fisher, Joseph O., 1926
  - Fretz, Paul H., Mrs., 1957
  - Friedrick, E., 1953, 1956-1959
  - Giles, Emma, 1949
  - Grant, Richard S., 1946
  - Hayes, John D., 1956
  - Hill, Andrew, Mrs., 1958
  - Hipp, Thomas E., 1946
  - Holmes, Ralston S., 1949-1950, 1952, 1954, 1956-1959
  - Hovgaard, William, 1926
  - Howard, Herbert S., 1926-1927
  - Jalbert, H. H., 1956
  - Jefferis, Jay H., 1926
  - Johnson, Mrs., 1904
  - Joyce, Charles S., 1926-1927
  - Kibbee, Austin, 1947-1948, 1658
  - Kintner
  - Lawrence, Ernest O., 1941
  - Leahy, L. R., 1947-1949, 1957-1958
  - Letter of recommendation, 1904
  - Lofquist, Emanuel A., 1926
  - Loggins, J. E., 1950
  - Loomis, Samuel, 1949, 1953-1954
  - MacDonell, Ella G., 1927
  - McGuigan, J. L., 1925
  - McNair, Frederick V., 1952, 1956, 1958, 1962
  - Metcalf, Louise M., 1949, 1952, 1956, 1958, 1962
  - Milne, MacGilivary, 1951-1956, 1958
  - Musser, Neil B., 1925-1927
  - Naile
  - Naval Academy Athletic Association, 1957-1958
  - Naval Attache at the American Embassy, London, 1932
  - Neill, John W., 1926
  - Parsons, B. F., 1899
  - Perry, Frederick A., 1927
  - Radford, George S., Mrs., 1950, 1956, 1958 (Box 2.)
  - Reichmuth, F. L., 1926
  - Robinson, S. M., 1949, 1958
  - Rock, George H., 1926-1927
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1936, 1943
  - Rowan, Steven, 1949, 1952, 1957-1958
  - Sadler, Frank H., 1951-1952, 1958
  - Schlabach, Ross P. and Mrs., 1951, 1957, 1960
  - Seamen's Church Institute of Newport, 1959
  - Shipmate (U.S. Naval Academy Alumni Monthly), 1956-1957
  - Smith, C. E.
  - Smith, Samuel W., 1899, 1903
  - Smyth, C. L., 1926
  - Social Security Agency, 1952
  - Stark, Admiral Harold, 1955
  - State of New Jersey. Executive Department, 1942
  - Taylor, F. H., 1951, 1958
  - U.S. Naval Academy. Preparatory School, 1899-1900
  - U.S. Naval Academy Alumni Association, 1944, 1946-1947, 1949, 1951, 1956
  - Van Keuren, James and family, 1899-1900, 1903-1906
  - Veterans Administration, 1946
  - Walder, R., Mrs., 1962
  - Ward, Richard
  - Webb Institute of Naval Architecture, 1946
  - Willson, J. D., 1927 (Box 3.)
  - Willson, Jean B., 1946
  - Miscellaneous
- NAVAL RESEARCH LABORATORY, ANACOSTIA STATION (Washington, D.C.), OFFICE FILE, 1942-1944
  - Akers, Frank, 1944 (Box 3.)
  - American Foundrymen's Association, 1944
  - American Ice Company, 1943
  - American Magazine, 1943
  - American Mercury, 1943
  - American Red Cross, 1943
  - Ashbrook, A. W., 1943
  - Autograph requests, 1943
  - B.F. Goodrich Company, 1943
  - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Company, 1944
  - Belknap, Charles, 1943
  - Binaural Sons of the "C", 1942-1944
  - Buckley, O. E., 1943
  - Burnett, H. A., 1943
  - Cargocaire Engineering Corporation, 1944
  - Cellers, M. Q., 1943
  - Chief of Bureau of Personnel, 1944
  - Clark, W. E., 1943
  - Combs, L. B., 1944
  - Commandant, Navy Yard, Mare Island, 1944
  - Crowell-Collier Publishing Company, 1943
  - Cutler, E. O., 1943
  - Department of the Navy. Bureau of Naval Personnel, 1944
  - Department of the Navy. Bureau of Ships, 1943
  - Dooley, John J., 1943
  - Duffield, Eugene S., 1944
  - Edison, Charles, 1943
  - Erthal, John F., 1943
  - Fairbank-Morse and Company, 1944
  - Foley, Paul, 1943-1944
  - Gibbs Gas Engine Company, 1944
  - Gifford, Roy W., 1943
  - Gleason, Hank M., 1943
  - Goulett, W. B., 1944
  - Hammond, Philip H., 1943-1944
  - Hanson, Ralph R., 1943
  - Hay, Marley R., 1943
  - Holmes, Ralston S., 1944
  - Hooper, J. C., 1943
  - Howell Lodge No. 38, Free and Accepted Masons, 1943
  - Hullick, C. V., 1943-1944
  - Internal Revenue Service
  - International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation, 1943
  - Isaacs, Morton, 1943
  - Jacobs, Randall, 1943
  - Kearfott Engineering Company, 1943
  - Leckie and Sherier, 1943
  - Link Belt Company, 1944
  - Little, Arthur D., 1943
  - Marquart, E. J., 1943-1944
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Alumni
  - Association, 1942-1943
  - Merchant Marine Council, 1944
  - Morgan, Frnak Allen, 1943
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1944
  - National Franklin Committee, 1943
  - National Inventor's Council, 1944
  - Naval Academy Alumni Association, 1943
  - Navy League of the United States, 1943
  - Navy Mutual Aid Association, 1943-1944
  - Newport News Shipbuilding and Dry Dock Company, 1943
  - New York Shipbuilding Corporation, 1943-1944
  - Norge Division, Borg-Warner Corporation, 1943
  - Office of Inspector of Naval Material, 1944
  - Office of War Information. Bureau of Intelligence, 1943
  - Overs, Williams C., 1943
  - Page, Stanley H., 1944
  - Paulding and Mears General Insurance, 1943
  - Procurement Officer, Naval Officer Procurement Program
  - 1943
  - Pullman Company, 1944
  - Radio Material Officer, Navy Yard, Mare Island, 1944
  - Richards, J. K., 1943
  - Rowland, Bertram Marshall, 1944
  - Schwab, Frances, 1943
  - Seattle-Tacoma Shipbuilding Corporation, 1944
  - Sharp, George, 1943
  - Shield, Marc, 1943
  - Shields, Edmund C., 1943
  - Shuttleworth, Samuel, 1943
  - Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers, 1943-1944
  - Stark, H. R., 1943 (Box 4.)
  - Stone, T. H., Mrs., 1944
  - Strauss, Lewis L, 1943
  - Sweeney, John L., 1943
  - Theleen, D. E., 1943-1944
  - Thoman, F. H., 1943
  - Thomson, Pembroke, 1943
  - Todd, David W., 1944
  - Toole, Brice, 1944
  - Turner, Thomas C., Mrs., 1944
  - U.S. Naval Academy Museum, Annapolis, 1943
  - U.S. Naval Dry Docks, Hunter's Point, San Francisco, 1944
  - U.S. Navy Radio and Sound Laboratory, San Diego, 1944
  - United States Rubber Company, 1943-1944
  - Vanderford, H. L., 1943
  - Van Keuren, Catherine, 1943
  - Van Keuren, Charles, 1943
  - Van Keuren, Francis C., 1943
  - Van Keuren, Marie, 1943
  - West, R. K., 1943
  - Wolcott, Robert W., 1943
  - Wood, Britton B., 1943
  - Yacaoubian, Vaughn, 1943
  - Ziff-Davis Publishing Company, 1943
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, memoranda, etc.
- NAVY DEPARTMENT ORDERS AND MEMORANDA, 1909-1945 (Box Box No 4.)
- SUBJECT FILE, ca. 1900-1960
  - Address before joint meeting of Howell and Lansing Rotary clubs by Admiral A. H. Van Keuren, October 15, 1930 (Box 5.)
  - Bell Bulletin Tech (Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, D.C.) 1943 - Vol. II, No. 17 (October)
  - Calling cards
  - Curriculum vitae
  - Geneva General Disarmament Conference, 1932
    - Correspondence
    - List of delegates and number of delegations
  - Invitations
  - Journal - U.S.S. Wisconsin Cruise, April 1903
  - Legion of Merit Award, signed by U.S. Secretary of the Navy James Forrestal
  - London Naval Conference, 1930
    - General
    - Correspondence and memoranda (Box 6.)
    - Invitations to social events
  - Navy Mutual Aid Society
  - The Newport Recruit1926 (Navy Day issue)
  - Philadelphia Navy Yard News, 1936-1937, Vol. 1-2, March-June
  - The Pilot (Naval Research Laboratory, Washington, D.C.) 1945 September
  - Progress reports on Admiral A. H. Van Keuren from U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., 1899-1900
  - Register of Commissioned and Warrant Officers of the United States Navy and Marine Corps, 1 July 1942
  - "The Sloop 'Providence'" by George L. Miner
  - The Stability of Ships and Damage Control (Department of the Navy)
  - Supplement to confidential bulletin No. 6, Public Works of the Navy: U.S. Naval Dry Docks, September 1911 (Box 7.)
  - "Tecumseh Annual" 1946
  - U.S. Naval Academy Alumni Association
  - "The Writings of Stephen B. Luce" by John D. Hayes (reprint from Military Affairs, Vol. XIX, No. 4, 1955)
- MISCELLANEOUS, ca. 1900-1960
  - Clippings (Box 7.)
  - Medals
  - Miscellaneous notes, printed matter, and memorabilia (Box 8.)
  - Certificate of membership (50 years), The Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers
  - Oversize items (at end of collection):(24) certificates, diplomas, marriage license, membership certificates, etc.